Merle Armitage papers, 1930-1974
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Merle Armitage papers, 1930-1974
MS 234
Armitage, Merle, 1893-1975
The collection contains an assortment of correspondence, books, some published by his Manzanita Press, typescripts of books and short stories, advertisements, illustrations, clippings, photographs and photographic plates, articles, speeches, catalogs, and miscellaneous original art work.
6 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Merle Armitage was an American author, publisher, book designer, graphic artist, and impresario.
Organization
This collection is organized into eight series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1947-1973
Series II: Books, Typescripts and Illustrations
Series III: Short Stories
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Printed Matter
Series VI: Personal Material
Series VII: Photographic Plates
Series VIII: Miscellaneous Art Work
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains an assortment of correspondence, books, some published by his Manzanita Press, typescripts of books and short stories, advertisements, illustrations, clippings, photographs and photographic plates, articles, speeches, catalogs, and miscellaneous original art work. The majority of the correspondence, 1958-60, is with George Mason regarding the book Stella Dysart, and with Ida Whitsett concerning the book Success Is No Accident. Typescript drafts and items relating to the publication of the books are also present.
Another set of correspondence is with the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railroad, 1958- 1973. Background materials relating to Armitage's book Homage to Santa Fe include the typescript draft, illustrations and advertisements, as well as railroad articles, timetables, and train photographs. Travel photographs from 1955 depict mainly the landscapes, monuments, and Native Americans in Arizona, New Mexico, California, and Oklahoma. Eighteen copper photographic plates are from the book Edward Weston: Fifty Photographs, and 22 more photographic plates are from other publications. Miscellaneous original art work is by Henrietta Shore, his daughter Chama Armitage, and Frank O'Brien. Other items are articles written by and about Armitage, speech typescripts, family mementos, material from his work as an impresario, and some of his original graphic designs.
Armitage, Merle, 1893-1975 -- Archives; O'Brien, Frank; Mason, George -- Correspondence; Whitsett, Ida -- Correspondence; Weston, Edward, 1886-1958; Shore, Henrietta, 1880-1963; Armitage, Chama; Manzanita Press; Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railroad Company -- History; Publishers and publishing -- California -- History -- 20th century; Book industries and trade -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Commercial artists -- United States; Small press books -- Specimens; Book design -- United States -- History; Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Correspondence; Photographic Plates; Photographs; Books; Illustrations
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1947-1973
  - General Correspondence. 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence. 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence. No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with: Atchison, Topeka and Sante Fe Railroads. 1958-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with: Duell, Sloan & Pearce. 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with: Dysart, Stella. 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with: Hurley, Pat J. (Gen.). 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with: Kistler, Lynton R. 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with: Lane Publishers. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with: Mason, George. November 1957-December 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with: Mason, George. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with: Smalley, Carl. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with: Verbeck, Howard. 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with: Whitsett, Ida and Paul. 1958?-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II: Books, Typescripts and Illustrations
  - Accent on Life (proofs). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Burro Alley (illustrations). (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Books for Our Times. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fit for a Queen (or King?) (illustrations). (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Five Essays on Klee. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Henrietta Shore (illustrations). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Homage to Santa Fe (typescript). (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Homage to Santa Fe (Railroad articles). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Homage to Santa Fe (Railroad photos). (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Homage to Santa Fe (Railroad timetables). (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Homage to Santa Fe (advertisements and illustrations). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pagans, Conquistadors, Heroes and Martyrs (illustrations). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lovet-Lorski (illustrations). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Modern Dance (advertisement). (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Martha Graham (advertisements). (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Operation Santa Fe (advertisement). (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Of Streets and Stars (book). (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pagans, Conquistadors & Martyrs (book). 1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Painter into Artist (book). (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Smile at the Foot of the Ladder (advertisement). (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Stella Dysart (typescript). (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Stella Dysart (clippings). (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Stella Dysart (photos). (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Success is no Accident (typescript). (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Success is no Accident (typescript). (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Success is no Accident (pp. 1-78, draft). (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Success is no Accident (pp. 79-136, draft). (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Success is no Accident (pp. 137-224, draft). (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Success is no Accident (pp. 225-292, draft). (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Success is no Accident (unidentified fragments). (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Success is no Accident (clippings). (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Navy (advertisement). (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Warren Newcomb (illustrations). (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified photos. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series III: Short Stories
  - "Case of the Missing Steak" (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Flying Gold" (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Jade" (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Keystone of the Arch" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Red Rogues" (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "San Simeon" (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Serbania" (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Transcontinental" (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Arizona: Canyon de Chelly. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Grand Canyon. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Indians. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Monument Valley. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Petrified Forest. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Rainbow Bridge. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Taliesen West. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Arizona: Miscellaneous Cities. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - California. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - New Mexico. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oklahoma. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Europe. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Animals, Reptiles, Birds, Insects. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Brush. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Cacti. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Rock Formations. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Art-photo copies. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series V: Printed Matter
  - Printed Matter designed by Merle Armitage. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Merle Armitage as art designer for "The Atom." (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Merle Armitage as art designer for Vision Magazine. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Merle Armitage as art designer for "Western Family." (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Book Advertisements (clippings). (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Merle Armitage. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Articles about Merle Armitage. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Book Catalog. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Published weekly catalogs containing Merle Armitage books. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Personal Material
  - "Look" at the Art Department. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Family Photos. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Speeches. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Merle Armitage as impresario (clippings). (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Book designing paraphernalia. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Photographic Plates
  - 18 plates from Edward Weston: Fifty Photographs. (Box 12)
  - 15 plates from Edward Weston and 7 plates from miscellaneous unidentified publications. (Box 13)
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous Art Work
  - Miscellaneous art work owned by Merle Armitage, Chama Armitage or Frank O'Brien. (Box 14)